Ren d'Harnoncourt Papers
The Museum of Modern Art, Publisher
Ren d'Harnoncourt Papers in The Museum of Modern Art Archives
1940-1968
59.25 linear feet of records Comprised of 139 boxes and 1 flat file: One hundred thirty (130) 10x5x15.5" boxes Two (2) 10x2.5x15.5" boxes One (1) 3.5x5.5x12.5" box One (1) 2.75x19.25x25.5" box Three (3) 1.75x15x19" boxes One (1) 4.5x12x17.75" box One (1) 5.5x17.5x21.5" box One (1) 2.5x52.5x41" drawer
The Museum of Modern Art Museum Archives 11 West 53 Street New York, NY 10019
Ren d'Harnoncourt
Personal and professional papers of Ren d'Harnoncourt, Director of MoMA, 1949-1968.
Provenance
Series I-IX accessioned into the Archives via internal transfer from the Directors Office. Series X donated to the Archives by Sarah d'Harnoncourt.
D'Harnoncourt, Rene, 1901-1968.; D'Harnoncourt, Rene, 1901-1968 -- Archives.; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.). International Council.; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.). International Program.; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.) -- Administration.; American Federation of Arts.; Committee on Government and Art.; Association on American Indian Affairs.; United States. Indian Arts and Crafts Board.; National Council on the Arts.; Unesco.; Indian art -- North America.; Indian art -- South America.; Indians of South America -- Andes Region.; Drawings.; Drawings.
Access Restrictions
The records are open for research and contain few restricted materials.
Biographical Note
Ren d'Harnoncourt was born in Vienna, Austria, on May 17, 1901. Both his parents were members of titled, landowning families, his fathers Austrian/French, and his mothers Czechoslovakian. His early years were spent in Graz, Austria, where he was educated privately until the age of ten. After attending schools in Graz during his teen years, he went in 1919 to the University of Graz where he studied chemistry and philosophy, transferring in 1922 to the Technische Hochschule in Vienna where he planned to take a degree in chemical engineering. He was, however, compelled for financial reasons to leave before completing his degree. (His family had lost money following the breakup of the Austro-Hungarian Empire after World War I.)
Although d'Harnoncourt's formal studies were concentrated in the sciences, he had from an early age been interested in art, and while at school and university had drawn and painted for his own enjoyment. At one time, he had, with friends, organized an exhibition of Matisse and Picasso prints in Graz. Graz was the home of one of the oldest museums in Europe devoted to primitive art, the Joanneum, and it is probable that it was here that d'Harnoncourt conceived his love for primitive art, which was to remain one of his lifelong passions.
In 1925 Ren d'Harnoncourt left Austria for Mexico City where he thought, mistakenly, that he could make a living as a scientist. After a year supporting himself by drawing posters and decorating store windows, he acquired a job selling antique furniture for a collector and antique dealer with whom he had been acquainted in Austria. This led to contacts with some well placed and affluent Americans who were collectors of antiques, among them William Green and his wife, and Alexander Weddell, American Consul General in Mexico. Through the Greens and Weddell d'Harnoncourt met Frederick Davis, an American who owned a store selling, among other things, Mexican art objects. At about the same time d'Harnoncourt met the American ambassador to Mexico, Dwight Morrow and his wife Elizabeth. The contacts with F. Davis and with the Morrows proved to be of enormous importance in d'Harnoncourt's life. Davis' shop was a sort of informal center for artists in Mexico City, and Davis asked d'Harnoncourt to organize an exhibition in the shop of works by three major Mexican artists, Diego Rivera, Jos Clemente Orozco, and Rufino Tamayo. In addition, Davis became a lifelong friend and provided d'Harnoncourt with a home in Mexico, a country d'Harnoncourt continued to love and visit after he had moved to the United States. Through his friendship with the Morrows, d'Harnoncourt made further contacts, and in 1929 was asked by the Mexican Ministry of Education to put together 48 collections of Mexican folk art - one for each of the United States - which would be sent to schools in each state to show children what was being done in Mexico.
The following year, d'Harnoncourt was asked - after arrangements had been made between the National Museum of Mexico and the Carnegie Corporation - to arrange a larger and more comprehensive exhibition of Mexican art, and take it to the United States himself. It was with this exhibition, sponsored by the American Federation of Arts, that d'Harnoncourt began his career in the United States. After a year spent collecting art objects from various parts of Mexico he started the tour on October 13, 1930 at the Metropolitan Museum in New York and proceeded on to seven more cities. Towards the end of 1931 he returned to Mexico to get official permission to extend the tour for a further year, after which he toured with the exhibition to six more cities. During this tour he met the trustees and staffs of the various museums where the exhibition was shown - contacts which would prove useful in his later career with MoMA.
Following his tour with the Mexican Arts exhibition, d'Harnoncourt went back to Austria, returning as an immigrant to the United States in 1933. In May of that year he married Sarah Carr whom he had met the previous year while on tour in Chicago. In 1939 he became a naturalized U.S. citizen.
During the period following his return to the United States until 1944 when he joined The Museum of Modern Art, d'Harnoncourt worked at several different places, starting with a two year stint directing a weekly radio program, Art in America, for NBC. During this period he was also employed part-time - and for a while full-time - at Sarah Lawrence College in Bronxville, New York, where he taught art history. In September 1936, while still teaching at Sarah Lawrence College, he was appointed as Assistant to the General Manager of the Indian Arts and Crafts Board, a division of the Department of the Interior in Washington. In June 1937 he became the Boards General Manager. In 1938 he was made responsible for assembling and installing the exhibition on Indian Art, sponsored by the Board for the San Francisco Golden Gate International Exposition in 1939. In 1940-41, as a guest curator, he installed a much-expanded version of this exhibition at MoMA. In 1943, while still working part-time as General Manager of the Indian Board, d'Harnoncourt was asked by Nelson Rockefeller to become Acting Director, Section of Art, Office of Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs, Department of State, of which Rockefeller was head.
In 1944 d'Harnoncourt was asked, at Rockefellers instigation, to join the staff of The Museum of Modern Art. He was given the titles Vice President in charge of Foreign Activities, and Director of the Department of Manual Industries. Both these titles relate to d'Harnoncourt's earlier positions in Washington, with the Foreign Activities position coinciding also with the international work done by MoMA since its founding. In 1942 he had been Chairman of a Committee on Manual Industries, attached to the Inter-American Development Committee, and his involvement with manual industries continued when he worked at the Coordinators Office. (Manual industries were considered to be of prime importance for the preservation of Indian art and culture, which were being threatened by mechanization.) d'Harnoncourt's involvement with manual industries and with his work in Washington continued during his first years at MoMA. As Vice President in charge of Foreign Activities, his work continued at first to focus on Latin America, and in December 1944 he began a three-month trip there to initiate a membership campaign for the Museum. The trip took him to Mexico, Peru, Chile, Argentina, Brazil, and Haiti. Following the end of World War II in 1945 contact with Europe increased, and in the summer of 1946 d'Harnoncourt was sent as a counselor on the arts to a UNESCO conference in London. In 1947 he became Director of the Curatorial Departments and Chairman of the Coordinating Committee. In October 1949 he was appointed Director of the Museum.
During his years as Director, the Museum celebrated its 25th and 30th anniversaries, marking the 30th anniversary with a fundraising campaign to finance expansion of the museum. The campaign was successfully managed by d'Harnoncourt and the Museum, which closed for a few months during construction and alterations celebrated its reopening with a new building on May 25, 1964. Among the many changes made in the Museum during d'Harnoncourt's time, one of the most important was the founding of the International Council in 1953. Of course, the main events at the Museum were its exhibitions, and d'Harnoncourt was involved with every one of them from the smallest to the large blockbusters. Some he directed himself; some he both directed and installed starting with the Arts of the South Seas in 1946 not long after he joined MoMA, and continuing with several major installations until his last much praised exhibition,The Sculpture of Picasso, in 1967.
Ren d'Harnoncourt retired from the Museum in June 1968, and a party was given in honor of him and his wife by Governor and Mrs. Nelson Rockefeller at their home in Pocantico Hills on June 11, 1968. He was elected an Honorary Trustee for Life and Counselor to the Trustees. Tragically, he was killed in an automobile accident near his summer home on the North Fork of Long Island a few weeks later on August 13, 1968.
Scope and Content Note
The papers document the major part of Ren d'Harnoncourt's life, covering in particular his years with The Museum of Modern Art, 1944-1968, and including also some records of his years in Mexico, and of his subsequent pre-MoMA career in the United States.
Ren d'Harnoncourt's Papers document, first and foremost, his career at The Museum of Modern Art, starting when he joined the Museum in 1944, and continuing through his years as Director from 1949 to his retirement in 1968. From the beginning, even before his official appointment as Director, it is apparent from the records that d'Harnoncourt was the right man to lead MoMA at this time. His overall accomplishment was to bring a level of order to an organization that after the resignation of Alfred Barr as Director, could have become mired in internal friction. d'Harnoncourt's correspondence both with the Museums trustees, and with its staff, reveal the gentle, good-humored, but decisive way in which he kept an equilibrium between all elements of the Museum community. In addition, he established a close working relationship with Alfred Barr, for whose knowledge of modern art and scholarship he had enormous respect. Among d'Harnoncourt's other major accomplishments at the Museum were the establishment of the International Council in the early 1950s - a task for which both his European background and his involvement with Latin America made him ideally suited - and his leadership of the 30th Anniversary fundraising campaign, culminating in the renovation and opening of the new Museum in 1964.
The installation by d'Harnoncourt of important exhibitions both in the Museum in New York and abroad, was, of course, another major accomplishment, especially as the installations had to be combined with his day-to-day work as Director of the Museum. In addition to the correspondence which comprises the greater part of d'Harnoncourt's papers, the collection also contains many of the superb drawings which he used in preparation for the exhibitions he installed. Particularly outstanding are drawings for the Arts of the South Seas exhibition shown at MoMA in 1946. Ren d'Harnoncourt's love for primitive art and his ability to use this love in the creation of what could be called blockbuster exhibitions is first shown in the records of the Mexican Arts exhibition with which he toured the United States in 1930-32. This was followed in 1939 and 1941 with the Indian Arts exhibitions, and later, in 1954 with Ancient Arts of the Andes. In 1957 d'Harnoncourt founded, with his friend and mentor, Nelson Rockefeller, the Museum of Primitive Art, of which he became Vice President and Rockefeller, President. The papers contain exhibition material - drawings, floor plans, wall captions - for many of d'Harnoncourt's other installations, culminating with his last exhibition, the very successful Sculpture of Picasso, shown at MoMA at the end of 1967.
Together, the correspondence and the exhibition material in the papers present a full picture of Ren d'Harnoncourt's life and accomplishments.
Arrangement
Series I: Museum Correspondence, U.S. and Abroad, 1930s-1940s
Series II: Latin American Correspondence, 1940s
Series III: General Correspondence, 1940s
Series IV: Directors Correspondence, 1949-1968
Series V: Special Events, 1949-1968
Series VI: MoMA International Council, 1952-1967
Series VII: Correspondence with Outside Organizations, 1940s-1968
Series VIII: Exhibitions Arranged and Directed by d'Harnoncourt, 1941-1968
Series IX: Art of Installation, 1930-1974
Subseries A: MoMA exhibitions at MoMA
Subseries B: MoMA exhibitions shown elsewhere
Subseries C: Exhibitions not related to MoMA
Subseries D: Typescripts of the book on the art of installation. Memos about the book, which was never published.
Series X: Sarah d'Harnoncourt Donation
Subseries A: Mexico, 1925-1932
Subseries B: U.S. before MoMA, 1933-1944
Subseries C: Years at MoMA, 1944-1968
1. Correspondence - speeches and honors
2. Correspondence - travel
3. Appointment Calendars
4. Articles by d'Harnoncourt (non-MoMA publications)
5. Articles about d'Harnoncourt
6. Articles by d'Harnoncourt (MoMA publications)
Subseries D: After d'Harnoncourt's Death, 1968-1980s
Subseries E. Personal Material
Series I through VIII have been maintained in the original order as created by d'Harnoncourt.
Subseries IX.A through IX.C, containing installation material, have been arranged according to sponsor and location of the exhibition. The material in subseries IX.D was received and has been maintained in no discernible order.
Subseries X.A through X.D have been rearranged into chronological subseries, with subseries C being further divided thematically. Subseries X.E contains personal material, which has been arranged chronologically. Series X has been placed at the end of the collection as it originated from a different source.
Additional Descriptive Data
Explanation of Abbreviations
ALS is an Autographed Letter Signed.
TLS is a Typed Letter Signed.
TL stands for Typed Letter.
MoMA is The Museum of Modern Art.
n.d. stands for no date.
re: stands for regarding.
RDH is Ren d'Harnoncourt
AHB is Alfred H. Barr, Jr.
NAR is Nelson A. Rockefeller
MW is Monroe Wheeler
JTS is James Thrall Soby
MoMA Exh. #, or just Exh. #, followed by a date, refers to the number assigned to the exhibition and the date it was shown at The Museum of Modern Art.
C/E refers to the national circulating version of the exhibition.
Dates that follow are the years during which the exhibition toured.
ICE refers to International Circulating Exhibition, an exhibition circulated under the auspices of the International Council.
ICE-D identifies exhibitions of works from foreign collections circulated in the United States and Canada.
ICE-F identifies exhibitions of works from the Museum's collections circulated internationally.
SP-ICE identifies Special Projects International Circulating Exhibitions including recurring international exhibitions, competitions, U.S. representations, and exhibitions funded, organized, and/or circulated by associations of public and private institutions.
File numbers marked by an asterisk (*) indicate oversize material.
Researchers should include the asterisk when issuing a request for such material.
List of MoMA Exhibitions Mentioned in Finding Aid
American Indian Art of the United States(Traveling Show) [C/E 1941-42]
Arts of the South Seas[MoMA Exh. #306, January 29-May 19, 1946]
Henry Moore[MoMA Exh. #339, December 17, 1946-Mar. 16, 1947]
Gabo - Pevsner[MoMA Exh. #369, February 10-April 25, 1948]
Elie Nadelman[MoMA Exh. #388, October 5-November 28, 1948]
Timeless Aspects of Modern Art[MoMA Exh. #393, November 16, 1948-January 23, 1949]
Modern Art in Your Life[MoMA Exh. #423, October 5-December 4, 1949]
International Competition for Low Cost Furniture Design[C/E 1950-52]
New Lamps[MoMA Exh. #473, March 27-June 3, 1951]
Henri Matisse[MoMA Exh. #492, November 13, 1951-January 13, 1952]
Ancient Arts of the Andes[MoMA Exh. #550, January 25-March 21, 1954]
Japanese Exhibition House[MoMA Exh. #559, June 16-October 21, 1954; April 26-October 15, 1955]
The Family of Man[MoMA Exh. #569, January 24-May 8, 1955]
French Masterworks: Fifteen Paintings by French Masters of the 19th Century from the Louvre and the Museum of Albi and Lyon[MoMA Exh. #572, February 25-April 24, 1955]
Textiles and Ornamental Arts in India[MoMA Exh. #576, April 11-September 25, 1955]
U.P.A (United Productions of America) Form in the Animated Cartoon[MoMA Exh. #581, June 22-September 27, 1955]
Latin American Architecture since 1945[MoMA Exh. #590, November 23, 1955-February 19, 1956]
Toulouse-Lautrec[MoMA Exh. #598, March 21-May 6, 1956]
Recent Drawings USA[MoMA Exh. #601, April 25-August 5, 1956]
Textiles USA[MoMA Exh. #606, August 29-November 4, 1956]
Buildings for Business and Government[MoMA Exh. #615, February 27-April 28, 1957]
Travel Posters[MoMA Exh. #616, March 6-April 7, 1957]
German Art of the 20th Century[MoMA Exh. # 622, Oct.2 - Dec. 1, 1957]
Seurat Paintings and Drawings[MoMA Exh. #629, March 24-April 15, 1958; May 1-May 11, 1958]
Jean Arp: A Retrospective[MoMA Exh. #631, October 8-November 30, 1958]
The Package[MoMA Exh. #647, September 9-November 1, 1959]
Three Structures by Buckminster Fuller[MoMA Exh. #649, September 22 - throughout the Winter]
New Images of Man[MoMA Exh. #651, September 30-November 29, 1959]
The Artist in his Studio - Photographs by Alexander Liberman[MoMA Exh. #653, October 29, 1959-January 13, 1960]
Art Nouveau[MoMA Exh. #666, June 8-September 6, 1960]
New Spanish Painting and Sculpture[MoMA Exh. #668, July 20-September 28, 1960]
Max Ernst[MoMA Exh. #680, March 1-May 8, 1961]
Steichen the Photographer[MoMA Exh. #682, March 28-May 30, 1961]
Futurism[MoMA Exh. #685, May 30-September 5, 1961]
15 Polish Painters[MoMA Exh. #690, August 1-October 1, 1961]
The Art of Assemblage[MoMA Exh. #695, October 4-November 12, 1961]
Chagall - The Jerusalem Windows[MoMA Exh. #697, November 19, 1961-Jan 3, 1962]
Redon-Moreau-Bresdin[MoMA Exh. #699, December 6, 1961-February 25, 1962]
Jean Dubuffet[MoMA Exh. #702, February 21-April 8, 1962]
Frank Lloyd Wright Drawings[MoMA Exh. #703, March 14-May 6, 1962]
Design for Sport[MoMA Exh. #706, May 15-July 29, 1962]
Art of the Asmat - The Collection of Michael C. Rockefeller[MoMA Exh. #709a, September 11-November 6, 1962]
Mark Tobey[MoMA Exh. #710, September 12-November 9, 1962]
The Bitter Years: 1935-41[MoMA Exh. #711, October 18-November 25, 1962]
Arshile Gorky 1904-1948[MoMA Exh. #716, December 19, 1962-February 12, 1963]
Le Corbusier: Buildings in Europe and India[MoMA Exh. #718, January 29-April 15, 1963]
Television U.S.A.: Thirteen Seasons[Lecture Series, February 5-May 4, 1963]
Emil Nolde: 1867-1956[MoMA Exh. #719, March 6-April 30, 1963]
Rodin[MoMA Exh. #721, May 1-September 8, 1963]
Americans 1963[MoMA Exh. #722, May 22-August 18, 1963]
Medardo Rosso: 1858-1928[MoMA Exh. #729, October 2-November 23, 1963]
Eduardo Paolozzi[MoMA Exh. #748, September 21-November 10, 1964]
Bonnard and His Environment[MoMA Exh. #749, October 7-November 29, 1964]
Gunter Haese[MoMA Exh. #750, October 16-November 15, 1964]
Architecture Without Architects[MoMA Exh. #752, November 11, 1964-February 7, 1965]
Max Beckmann[MoMA Exh. #754, December 16, 1964-January 31, 1965]
The Responsive Eye[MoMA Exh. #757, February 25-April 25, 1965]
Modern Architecture, U.S.A.[MoMA Exh. #767a, May 18-September 6, 1965]
Giacometti[MoMA Exh. #768, June 9-October 12, 1965]
Robert Motherwell[MoMA Exh. #776, October 1-November 28, 1965]
Structures for Sound - Musical Instruments by Francois & Bernard Baschet[MoMA Exh. #777, October 5, 1965-January 23, 1966]
Sculpture in Glass[MoMA Exh. #780, November 16, 1965-January 2, 1966]
Ren Magritte[MoMA Exh. #782, December 15, 1965-February 27, 1966]
Dorothea Lange[MoMA Exh. #789, January 26-April 10, 1966]
Turner: Imagination and Reality[MoMA Exh. #794, March 23-June 19, 1966]
Louis I. Kahn[MoMA Exh. #797, April 26-May 30, 1966]
Reuben Nakian[MoMA Exh. #799, June 22-September 5, 1966]
The Racing Car: Toward a Rational Automobile[MoMA Exh. #806, September 27-November 27, 1966]
The New Japanese Painting and Sculpture[MoMA Exh. #809, October 19, 1966-January 2, 1967]
The Taste of a Connoisseur: Paul J. Sachs Collection[MoMA Exh. #815, December 21, 1966-March 5, 1967]
The New City: Architecture and Urban Renewal[MoMA Exh. #818, January 24-March 13, 1967]
Once Invisible[MoMA Exh. #833, June 20-September 11, 1967]
The Sculpture of Picasso[MoMA Exh. #841, October 11, 1967-January 1, 1968]
The Sidney and Harriet Janis Collection[MoMA Exh. #848, January 17-March 4, 1968]
Related Collections at MoMA and Elsewhere
The Public Information Records include extensive clippings regarding nearly every Museum exhibition, personality, and event.
For complementary exhibition-related materials, please consult the Registrar Exhibition Files. Similarly, the Department of Circulating Exhibitions (C/E) Records include information regarding MoMA exhibitions that toured domestically, and the International Program Records include documentation regarding International Circulating Exhibitions (ICE) of The Museum of Modern Art.
At the Rockefeller Archive Center, 15 Dayton Avenue, Sleepy Hollow, NY 10591, the Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers and the Blanchette H. Rockefeller Papers in the Rockefeller Family Archives contain related materials.
Record Group 4 (Nelson A. Rockefeller, Personal) contains two relevant series - Art and Projects. The Art series has the records of Rockefellers art collection, and the Projects series includes the records of his work with museums, in particular, The Museum of Modern Art and the Museum of Primitive Art. Rockefeller was President (1946-53), and Chairman of the Board (1956-58), of The Museum of Modern Art while d'Harnoncourt was at the Museum. The Museum of Primitive Art was co-founded by Rockefeller and d'Harnoncourt.
The Blanchette H. Rockefeller Papers (Record Group 53) contain material related to Mrs. Rockefellers extensive work as a Trustee of The Museum of Modern Art.
An oral history of Ren d'Harnoncourt, interviewed by Isabel Grossner in 1968, can be found at Columbia University, Oral History Research Office, 801 Butler Library, 535 West 114 Street, New York, NY 10027.
The Archives of American Art holds a small amount of d'Harnoncourt Papers, particularly relating to his interest in Mexico. The Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution, 750 9th St. NW, Suite 2200, Washington, DC 20560.
Container List
- Series I: Museum Correspondence, U.S. and Abroad, 1930s-1940s
  This series links Ren d'Harnoncourt with the early history of the Museum. It includes material which predates d'Harnoncourt's involvement with the Museum, such as correspondence between Alfred H. Barr, Jr. and Jere Abbott and other museums in the U.S. and abroad, as well as records from the 1940s and d'Harnoncourt's first years at the Museum.
  - Foreign Museums - Austria, 1948; Brief correspondence with the Albertina, Vienna. (Folder I.1)